+91- 9823544840 dsjdsouza@gmail.com B 501 Runwal Daffodils, NIBM Undri Road, Pune-411060

Dr (Col) Derek SJ DSouza

BDS, MDS, MBA (HR), F.IIOPM (UK)

Professional Profile: SENIOR MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT – Organisational Psychological Medicine, Healthcare, Learning & Development.

- ➤ International Healthcare Trainer & Consultant Organisational Psychological Medicine
- Director Student Training & Development Dr DY Patil Vidyapeeth University Pune
- Co-Chair Intl Training Courses, Dept of Education, Intl Chair in Bioethics, Melbourne
- Former Director, National Bioethics Curriculum Implementation Centre, Pune, India
- Track record of over 2 decades of meritorious service with Indian Army spearheading Healthcare Management, HR Administration, Learning & Development initiatives
- Extensive experience in conceptualizing, implementing SOP's, training programmes, process improvement, resource allocation, costing and utilization in healthcare operations



A decorated AD Corps Officer with over 30 years of total experience; presently associated with with Dr DY Patil Vidyapeeth Pune as Director (Student Training & Development), Co-Chair and Head Head International Training Courses, Dept of Education, International Chair in Bioethics, Melbourne Australia; Former Director, National Bioethics Curriculum Implementation Centre; Rich and varied expertise in managing entire healthcare operations with key focus on top line & bottom line profitability by ensuring optimal utilization of resources.

- > Attended / organised high profile professional seminars, webinars and workshops in India and abroad to keep abreast with latest developments in healthcare trends as well as administrative techniques; versatile professional accredited with research works, publications and presentations
- > Track record of maintaining excellent relationships with businesses, communities, vendors and other stakeholders to promote newer business opportunities, resulting in increased revenue for the organization.

Work Experience

Since Jul 2021 till date with Dr DY Patil Vidyapeeth Pune as Director, Student Training & Development and Director, International Relations Centre, DPU. Also Co-Chair, and Head, International Training Courses, Dept of Education, International Chair in Bioethics, Melbourne Australia. From Apr 2017 to Jul 2021 with MIMER Medical College as Director, NBCIC, National Head Training Indian Program UNESCO Chair in Bioethics Haifa and Professor Dept of Dentistry.

Feb 2015 to Apr 2017 with Sikkim Manipal Institute of Medical Sciences as Professor and Head, Dept of Dentistry; Officer-in-charge Admissions; Director Purchase; (Healthcare Management, HR Administration, Learning & Development)

- Conducted training workshops and faculty development courses in Bioethics, Stress Management, Personality Development, Medical Ethics, Soft Skills Training, Communication etc in India and abroad.
- National Head Training Courses, Indian Program UNESCO Chair in Bioethics (Haifa) Conducted training of medical and dental faculty all across the country as part of the 3T Bioethics Training Indian Programme of the UNESCO Chair Bioethics (Haifa). Helped in development of the vertically integrated curriculum for bioethics in all healthcare disciplines.
- Healthcare / HR Management: Providing planning and implementation of strategic healthcare policies encompassing end-to-end healthcare management.

- Healthcare Technical Instruction & Evaluation: Designing, implementing and managing numerous technical undergraduate training programs as well as conducted seminars and hands-on training courses.
- Logistics Material Management Operations and Planning: Director Purchase, Keenly involved in Operations Management, Personnel Administration, Medical Stores Inventory Management and Health care capacity Expansion Projects; marshaling limited resources to maximize productivity to achieve healthcare targets; budget and financial administration.

Aug 2014 to Feb 2015 with M A Rangoonwala College of Dental Sciences and Research Centre As Head of Administration

- Managing & overseeing the administrative & daily operations of the Dental College, ensuring compliance with the policies and regulations; developing, implementing & maintaining policies, objectives and plans; managing budgets
- Providing leadership to teaching and administrative staff & supervising the guidance & discipline of students; ensuring that staff appraisals are carried out annually
- Researching, establishing and implementing program reviews and outcome assessment criteria, standards, systems & procedures and integrating the same into future departmental planning
- Supervising a large staff of doctors and managing the operations including, budgeting, personnel, HR, technology & spearheading teams for excelling business targets & service delivery metrics
- Engaging in procurement, planning and budgeting of medical and general stores

Oct 1992 to Aug 2014 with Army Dental Corps (Armed Forces Medical Services)

As Various Designations in Army Dental Corps (Healthcare Management, HR Administration, Learning & Development)

- Healthcare / HR Management: Providing vision in planning and implementation of strategic healthcare policies encompassing end-to-end healthcare management,
- Post graduate Technical Instruction & Evaluation: Designing, implementing and managing numerous technical post-graduate training programs as well as conducted seminars and briefing sessions
- Logistics Material Management Operations and Planning: Exploiting skills in Operations Management, Personnel Administration, Medical Stores Inventory Management and Capacity Expansion Projects.

Major Deputations with Highlights

Oct 2011 to Aug 2014 with Command Military Dental Centre, Jaipur As Deputy Commandant

- Spearheaded entire spectrum of specialist and routine Oral healthcare co-ordination, planning and delivery activities with key involvement in management of Specialist & Emergency Dental Teams including training and deployment
- Headed Logistics, Medical Stores and Financial activities of entire South-Western Zone
- Key member in recruitment of technical manpower, staffing and deployment of Veterans Healthcare facilities
- Worked closely with senior-level management in Army and Command Headquarters for long-term strategic healthcare planning
- Designed and executed establishment of new Command Military Dental Centre (SWC) for South Western Army

Nov 2009 to Oct 2011 with Military Dental Centre, Pathankot As Commanding Officer and Classified Specialist Prosthodontics

- Evolved and implemented clinical hands-on, career guidance and leadership training modules for officers and students
- Key member in technical manpower recruitment, staffing and deployment of Veterans Healthcare facilities
- Established new protocols for maxillofacial care and protocols for establishment of Regional Blood Bank Centre.

Dec 2004 to Nov 2009 with Military Dental Centre (CME) / AFMC Pune

As Associate Professor and Technical Instructor

- Served in various positions of responsibilities spanning
- Certified Technical Instructor & Trainer at Armed Forces Medical College Pune
- Recognised Postgraduate Teacher of Prosthodontics at the Armed Forces Medical College, Pune
- Postgraduate Examiner of Maharashtra University of Health Sciences, Nasik
- Postgraduate Examiner in Prosthodontics for Armed Forces Medical Services
- Member Inspection team on behalf of Dental Council of India
- Faculty member Medical Education Department AFMC Pune
- Instrumental in establishing new protocols for admission cell at AFMC for 2008 and 2009 and for enhanced Post graduate training in Prosthodontics
- Integrally involved in technical and hands-on training UG Medical Cadets, PG Residents and Para-dental Staff

Mar 2001 to Apr 2003 with Indo-Bhutan Friendship Hospital, Thimphu, Bhutan As Specialist Dental Officer & In-charge - Oral Healthcare Section

- Played a crucial role as part of Indian Military Training Team for logistics and services support
- Created history by establishing Specialist Treatment Protocols in Prosthodontics for the first time in the country
- Introduced various Oral cancer awareness programmes as well as conducted oral cancer screening camps
 Jun 1998 to Mar 2001 with Command Military Dental Centre, New Delhi / Chandigarh
 As Specialist Dental Officer & Administrative Officer
- Played a significant role in relocating the entire Command Dental Centre from New Delhi to Chandigarh in record time
- Established Tertiary Oral healthcare set-up with optimum utilization of available resources resulting in significant savings to the exchequer

Professional Accolades

- Received Commendation as Best International Trainer from UNESCO Chair in Bioethics Haifa Jerusalem in Nov 2018
- General Officer Commanding-in-Chief Commendation Medal for distinguished service in Indian Army, Aug 2014
- Chief of Army Staff Commendation Medal for distinguished service in the Indian Armed Forces, on Jan 2010
- Best Referee of the Medical Journal Armed Forces India by Editorial Review Committee for year 2012 and 2015, 2019, 2020.
- Lt. General KS Master Gold Medal for standing First in the Senior Dental Officers Course for year 2004
- Lt. General KS Master Gold Medal for standing First in Prosthodontics for year 1998
- Received the Neolabs Silver Medal for standing Second in Calcutta University at Final BDS Examinations in 1991

Technical Publications

Written a chapter in each of the books as under:

- Textbook of Bioethics, Medical Ethics and Health Law
- 'Oral Health Care Prosthodontics, Periodontology, Biology, Research and Systemic Conditions'.
- 'Current Concepts in Dental Implantology', published by InTech Publishers and edited by Dr Ilser Turkyilmaz
- 'Tuesday Dental Clinics of AFMC' published by Armed Forces Medical College Pune
- 'Patient Safety Protocols' in 'Handbook on Patient Safety' published by Armed Forces Medical College Pune
- 'Specific Learning Objectives' in Handbook 'Introduction to Medical Education Technology' at AFMC, Pune
- Published an E- book titled "Oral Health A Compendium of Care" in February 2014
- Member Editorial Team of the book titled 'Military Dentistry' on the Army Dental Corps
- Member Editorial Team of Coffee Table Book titled "Army Dental Corps Trails and Triumphs" on AD Corps
- Part of the Editorial Review Committee of the Medical Journal Armed Forces India An Indexed Journal
- Reputed Guest Speaker at numerous National and International Conferences in Medical Sciences, Bioethics.
- Many scientific publications in National and International Journals

Education & Credentials

- 2018 Fellowship in Organisational Psychological Medicine (UK)
- 2016 MBA Human Resource Management from Sikkim Manipal University (DE)
- 2016 ETTC course by UNESCO at SRM University in Apr 2016
- 2015 Workshop on Bioethics at SMIMS.
- 2007 Medical Education Technology Course from Armed Forces Medical College Pune
- 2004 Classified Specialist Denatl Officers Course Prosthodontics
- 2003 Senior Dental Officers Professional & Command Course Gold medallist
- 1998 MDS (Prosthodontics) from Mumbai University
- 1998 Graded Specialist Prosthodontics from Armed Forces Medical College Pune Gold medallist
- 1992 BDS from Dr R Ahmed Dental College, Kolkata Silver medallist

Membership Of Professional Societies

- Fellow, International Institute of Organisational Psychological Medicine (IIOPM)
- Member, International Forum of Teachers of Bioethics, Medical University, Sofia, (E.U.)
- Life Member of Indian Prosthodontic Society
- Life Member Society for Oral Laser Applications

Personal Profile:

Permanent Address : B 501 Runwal Daffodils, NIBM Undri Road Pune 411060

• Date of Birth : 12 Apr 1968

• Languages Spoken : English, Hindi, Bengali.

Declaration:

I do hereby declare that the information provided above is true to the best of my knowledge and belief.

Place: Pune

Date: 01 June 2023 Col (Dr) DSJ DSouza